<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Memoires of the life of Anthony, late Earl of Shaftsbury with a speech of the English consul at Amsterdam concerning him, and a letter from a burger there about his death.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1671</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R902</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12770201</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12770201</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93643</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50580)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93643)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 698:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Memoires of the life of Anthony, late Earl of Shaftsbury with a speech of the English consul at Amsterdam concerning him, and a letter from a burger there about his death.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Davis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682/3.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>From t.p.: "Offered to the consideration of the Protestant dissenters."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, --  Earl of, (1621-1683)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93643:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MEMOIRES OF THE LIFE OF ANTHONY LATE Earl of Shaftsbury; WITH A SPEECH OF THE Engliſh Conſul at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> concerning him, AND A LETTER From a BURGER there about his Death. <hi>Offered to Conſideration of the Proteſtant Diſſenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Walter Davis, featuring a black horse</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>MIEVEX VAVLT MOVRIR E VERTV QUE VIVRE EN HONCTE</q>
               </head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for WALTER DAVIS. 1682/3.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:93643:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93643:2"/>
            <head>MEMOIRES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing which of late hath been more ſurprizing than the conſideration of the wonderful Induſtry which a ſort of Deluded People, for ſo in charity I would di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh ſome of them, from others who act out of Malice, Intereſt, and Revenge, and what pains they have taken to make themſelves and all others uneaſy: and to ſee this toilſome and laborious Diligence, ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitably and in its natural and moſt rational conſequences, tending to the pulling down upon their own heads the united vengeance of Heaven and Earth, the ſeverity of Humane Laws, which by provoking, they daily exaſperate to uſe the utmoſt rigor, and the more terrible and inexorable puniſhments of Hell and Damnation, as certainly the portion of thoſe who reſiſt the Higher Powers as that there is a God, and that the Scriptures are ſo true, that <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away,</hi> but not <hi>one</hi> ſingle <hi>Iota</hi> of thoſe <hi>dreadful Comminations</hi> paſs unfulfilled. This conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as it increaſes my aſtoniſhment, ſo it moves my compaſſion; nor is the <hi>Compaſſion</hi> I have for the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> for ſuch indeed are all thoſe who are commonly called <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>eò Nomine</hi> puniſhed by the Laws of the Civil Government, the Peace of which they diſturb and endanger, only a bare <hi>pity,</hi> which looks no farther then a few tender Expreſſions, <hi>Alas poor Creatures!</hi> or <hi>God help them!</hi> or ſuch like; but I have long had in my thoughts to do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that might tend to their real advantage, and ſecure them from the dangerous Precipice of Ruin here, and Damnation hereafter, upon which they ſeem to ſtand.</p>
            <p>It is the misfortune of theſe People, to have the blind lead the blind, their pretended Guides blinded with Rage, and the fear of loſing their Shrine-making, which brings them in their Gains, will not let them ſee their danger, but exhort them to obſtinacy againſt the Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, under the colour of Conſtancy and ſuffering Perſecution for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, when there is not the leaſt foundation of truth in it; and they wildly buoy them up with expectations of ſome miraculous deliverance from Heaven, while in the mean time, they endeavour to draw all their hopes of aſſiſtance from Hell; and ſupport them in their obſtinacy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Laws, and their Lawful Governours, by the expectation of a revolution in the Government it ſelf, which they have and do with their utmoſt art and induſtry endeavour to undermine and overthrow.</p>
            <p>The ſucceſsleſs attempts they have of late made againſt it, would if they would ſit down and beſtow a few moments cool Reflection, be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to convince them, that they are not at all either the Care or the Favourites of Heaven; and I am perſwaded, that would they but ſee how like <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Chariots, and his Horſe-men, and all his Hoſt, they have purſued the Church into the midſt of the Sea, and that the Waves
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93643:3"/>have begun to return towards their ſtrength, that the Wheels of their Chariots have been ſo often taken off, and have driven ſo heavily, they would be obliged to ſay with the <hi>Egyptians, Let us fly from the face of the Engliſh Iſrael, for God ſighteth for them againſt the Egyptian Diſſenters;</hi> and I wiſh they do not by their obſtinacy drive the Allegory too far, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent when it is too late.</p>
            <p>Among all the variety of thoughts upon which I might fix, in order to do this miſerable and miſtaken People a real kindneſs, I could not think of any more proper, than the expoſing to their view one of the great occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of their Deluſion, the late E. of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> the diſeaſes of whoſe Mind lay in a great meaſure concealed from their eyes ſo long as he lived, as many times thoſe of the Body do to the moſt learned ſons of <hi>Hermes,</hi> till the death of their Patients, does by diſſection of their bodies give ſatisfaction to their doubts and curioſity; and not only ſo, but may be of advantage too to the living, by ſhewing the true cauſes of ſome effects, which were before wholly unknown, and therefore incurable: And truly this is the principal reaſon of this Anatomy Lecture upon the Life and Death of that Noble Peer. And if we find in his Character, that his <hi>Religion</hi> was always calculated for the Latitude of his <hi>Intereſts</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns,</hi> that he could therefore certainly have <hi>none,</hi> who could be occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally contented with <hi>any;</hi> that he could under an Uſurper countenance and promote the trampling down of the Laws and Liberties of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Nation, and therefore could not by inward Principles be an Enemy either to Popery or Arbitrary Government; it may be a means to <hi>unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> ſuch as have been <hi>ſeduced</hi> by his Speeches and Profeſſions, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him ſo great a Pillar of the Proteſtant Religion, and ſo ſtrong a Baſtion againſt Arbitrary Government; and not only ſo, but may teach them for the future, to give no credit to any ſuch, who hereafter by a sTATE <hi>Metempſychoſis,</hi> ſhall ſeem to have received the Soul of <hi>Shaft sbury</hi> by tranſmigration, and ſhall with the ſame principles and pretences ſtand in oppoſition to the eſtabliſhed Government, and thereby endeavour to maintain their Ground, and ſecure their own heads from puniſhment, by courting and animating a Popular Faction to oppoſe the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which in all humane probability muſt end in the ruin and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thoſe refractory and obſtinate oppoſers of the Peace and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Nation. I know it will look like a cowardly and ungenerous inſolence, to tread hard upon the fame of the Dead, and if it contradicts the old Proverb, <hi>De mortuis nil niſi bonum,</hi> to ſpeak <hi>well</hi> of the Dead, I muſt ſay this by way of Anticipation to that Objection, that the dead muſt firſt have <hi>deſerved</hi> to be <hi>well ſpoken</hi> of; and that the intention of this Paper was never level'd at ſo low a mark as to trample upon the Fame of his Lordſhip, but to prevent the <hi>miſchiefs</hi> which yet he may do even af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death, if the world ſhall ſtill be permitted to go on in the belief that his Lordſhip was all that which he pretended to be; and others who ſhall ſtep up into the place of this head of the <hi>Hydra,</hi> which Providence hath newly cut off, ſhall be alſo ſuppoſed to ſucceed him in thoſe imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Qualifications and Excellencies of Zeal for his Country and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, which this Paper undertakes to demonſtrate he was as far from, as <hi>Catiline,</hi> or <hi>Sejanus,</hi> or their far ſurpaſſing <hi>Oliver,</hi> ever were from being <hi>Friends</hi> to their Country, the Liberty, Peace and Happineſs of the People who had the misfortune to be under the power of their Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93643:3"/>
            <p>This Noble Peer was born in the County of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> to a competent good fortune, but with a ſpirit which very early ſhewed he was of a tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent, reſtleſs and changeable Temper, rather ſubtile than Politick, and malicious than Wiſe; and to contribute to this unſetled humour, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in Religion, he was committed in his Minority to the tuition of one Mr. <hi>Strong,</hi> a Nonconformiſt Miniſter, whom afterwards, in gratitude, he got preferred for his Excellent Talent in haranguing the People a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King and the eſtabliſhed Government both in Church and State, to be placed at St. <hi>Margarets</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> as I doubt not but diverſe ſtill living there can remember: From this Miniſter he received thoſe early prejudices againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> which ſtuck by him to his laſt; and it may be, the wanting of a good Foundation of that Apoſtolical and Primitive Chriſtianity taught and maintained in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> did not only prejudice him againſt that conſtitution and form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but gave him, as it hath done thouſands beſides, thoſe looſe and rolling ſands of opinion, which makes them ſhift their Religion with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very tide of alteration in matters of State.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Anthony Aſhley Cooper,</hi> for ſuch was then his Title, was very young at the breaking out of the late Horrid Rebellion raiſed by the Faction of <hi>Diſſenting</hi> Proteſtants, which were united in one common intereſt (the only way that I know of Uniting Diſſenters) againſt the King and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed Church and Government; and in the beginning of the Civil War, he was Captain of a Troop of Horſe in the Royal Party, though there do not remain upon Record any great Monuments of his Chivalry; but the Kings affairs beginning, after many ſharp conflicts with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, to be in ſome diſorder, the young Knight Errant, who was reſolved that Victory ſhould be his Miſtreſs; upon what party ſoever ſhe beſtows her ſmiles, quickly turned Apoſtate, and at the ſame time, with his Troop, quitted his Loyalty and the Kings Service.</p>
            <p>The young Deſerter, who now began to ſet up for a Polititian, was a very welcome man among the Traitors, for this ſeaſonable Treaſon; and it was not long before he got into the Commons Houſe, where he met with notable Tutors in Antimonarchical, Rebellious, and Seditious Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks; and his natural Talents lying that way, he quickly grew a Profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in all the Arts of traducing the King, his Miniſters and Government, and haranguing the Nation out of all the little remainders of Loyalty, by frighting them with the Dangers and Fears of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi> with which as they had firſt excited the People of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sects and Schiſms, <hi>Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptiſts, Browniſts,</hi> &amp;c. to rebel, ſo they animated them to perſiſt deſperately in that unnatural War, by telling them, <hi>that ſhould the King and Royal Party prevail, Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Arbitrary Power would inevitably ſwallow up all.</hi> By theſe Arts they prevailed to that degree, that the whole World was a witneſs of the infamous Tragedy, which was acted upon the Perſon of the moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Prince King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Firſt.</p>
            <p>But it happening that the Traitors who had been <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimous</hi> ſo long as the King had either Intereſt, Power or Life, which they could fear, when by taking away his, they thought they had ſecured their own lives, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having divided the Kings and Church Lands, and the ſpoil of the whole Nation, among themſelves, this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nton</hi> came to be <hi>diſſolved;</hi> and the <hi>Independents</hi> having ſupplanted the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in the Army, the Army were reſolved to diſſolve the Parliament, and Rule by the power of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93643:4"/>the Sword: And here our little Polititian again turns Renegado to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as before he had done to the King; and judging that <hi>Oliver</hi> was now like to be the Supream Governour of the Nation, he immediately ſtrikes in with his Intereſt, and contributes his utmoſt endeavours to make him Lord Protector of the three Kingdoms; and that he might rivet himſelf the cloſer into the favour of the Uſurper, he was very ſollicitous to marry <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s Daughter, that ſo though he could not have the honor himſelf, his Poſterity however might come to be Princes of the Blood: But though he was not very ſucceſsful in his Amours, yet he was in his Politicks ſtill, for he got to be of the Protectors <hi>Council of State,</hi> where, to the Book, his Hand, <hi>A. A. Cooper,</hi> may be ſeen to a thouſand of the moſt Arbitrary, Illegal, and Tyrannical Orders, for the raiſing of Money <hi>without</hi> Act of Parliament, and for <hi>impriſoning</hi> the Subjects contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the ſo much Magnified <hi>Petition of Right:</hi> Nay his little Honor, for he was not yet a Peer, was alſo then a violent Perſecutor of the People of the Lord, following the example of <hi>Oliver,</hi> and the thriving Religion, who filled the Jails with <hi>Quakers,</hi> notwithſtanding they were very good <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> and many of them had been helpful to him, in <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Meroz, and fighting the Lords Battels againſt the Mighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The diſappointment however of the honour of being the Protectors Son-in-Law, did not a little ſhock the Ambition of Sir <hi>Anthony,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a moſt admirable faculty of never forgiving any perſon, or to ſpeak in his own Language, having ever the good fortune to be <hi>revenged</hi> upon thoſe who did him <hi>any injury,</hi> though for the preſent he put it in his Pocket, yet it was but as he did his Book of <hi>Memoires,</hi> to be ready upon occaſion to return it with a vengeance; and therefore the ſame whirlwind that hurried away <hi>Oliver,</hi> inſpired the Triple-named Knight with reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to quit ſcores with that trifle of a Protectoret <hi>Richard,</hi> for the ſins of his Father <hi>Oliver,</hi> in refuſing him his alliance: So ſoon therefore as he ſaw Queen <hi>Dick</hi> begin to totter in the Coach-box of Government, he was reſolved to have one whip or two at the pamper'd Jades in the Harneſs, not doubting but to break the neck of the <hi>Charrioteer,</hi> although his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had the fortune to eſcape the danger of the Horſes preſented to him by the <hi>German</hi> Prince in <hi>Hyde-Park;</hi> he got in therefore with the <hi>Rump,</hi> who voted down <hi>Richard</hi>'s highneſs into plain <hi>Dick Cromwell</hi> again; and in all thoſe ſeveral turns, where the Government was made a meer Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball, and now the <hi>Rump</hi> run away with it, then the <hi>Committee of Safety</hi> got a kick at it, ſometimes <hi>Wallingford-Houſe</hi> had it at their foot, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Lambert</hi> and his <hi>Levellers,</hi> Sir <hi>Anthony</hi> ſtill was at the Goal of the Winning Party, ever giving thoſe whoſe heels were laſt tript up the Go-by; as true to his Principles as the reeling <hi>Needle</hi> in a Storm is to its beloved <hi>North,</hi> which though it be twirled about the 32 points of the Compaſs, yet at laſt ſettles and points to its kind Star: So did our Knight, who was always reſolved to be ſomebody, and to ſail by the Star of his own Intereſt, let the wind blow from what quarter of the World it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>The Nation grown weary of this tumbling and toſſing of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment from one hand to another of the <hi>Factious true Proteſtant Rebels,</hi> begun after the dear bought Experience of being ſeduced, at the rate of ſo many Millions of Treaſure and whole Seas of Chriſtian blood, to grow weary of the pretended Reformation and Reformers, of the ſtanding Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Major Generals, Free Quarter, and Endleſs Taxations, with which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93643:4"/>they were oppreſſed, to defend that Freedome and Liberty which they found was in reality a moſt intolerable ſlavery; and now it was evident that Ship-money and all the Monopolies, were but as a <hi>little finger</hi> of the Kings compared to the <hi>Loins</hi> or <hi>Rump</hi> of a Parliament, and there ſeemed to be ſuch an <hi>Univerſal Wiſh</hi> throughout the three Nations, for the Reſtauration of the King, our now Gracious Soveraign, that wiſe Men every where now began to ſee it muſt be ſo; the beſt moſt ardently hoping it, and the worſt who feared it, ſtruck with ſuch a pannick fear and horror that they durſt not oppoſe it; and General <hi>Monk</hi> who with the firſt perceived the <hi>Motion</hi> of the Angel in this <hi>Troubled Pool,</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to help the <hi>Cripled</hi> Kingdoms into the Water, that they might be <hi>healed.</hi> And here our Polititian made a moſt meritorious virtue of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, as many others of the Faction did, who glory much of their <hi>help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to reſtore his Majeſty, when in truth, they ſaw if they <hi>did not,</hi> it would be done <hi>without</hi> their help. Sir <hi>Anthony</hi> finding the wind freſhing up thus ſtrongly for the Coaſt of <hi>Loyalty,</hi> brought all his Tacks aboard, and ſtood in with <hi>Monk</hi> with all the Sail he could make, to bring in the King, cunningly foreſeeing that this would bring him into Reputation and Play again <hi>under</hi> Monarchy, as he had before been <hi>againſt</hi> it; but for a parting blow however, he was one of thoſe who thought to have broken <hi>Monk</hi>'s neck, and thereby have made their own Game, by impoſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him that <hi>Arbitrary Order</hi> and the <hi>greateſt affront</hi> that was ever done to the City of <hi>London,</hi> by pulling down their Gates, Poſts and Chains, and marching his whole Army into the City. Theſe were then no <hi>Crimes</hi> with Sir <hi>A. A. Cooper,</hi> no <hi>Violations</hi> of the City Charter; though lately the marching of the Royal Guards through it, and the Guards them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, have by him and his Party been thought and called a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Standing Armies</hi> and <hi>Illegal, Arbitrary, Mercenary Popiſh Guards,</hi> and motions made not to permit any of them to march through the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, in comes the King, and (with his Auguſt and Sacred Perſon and Government) Law, Liberty and the beſt Reformed Government and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the World, Peace and Plenty Crown the Land, Joy and Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſmiles in every Face, nay the greateſt of his own and his Fathers Enemies, the <hi>infamous Regicides</hi> only excepted, drink Brimmers of the Royal Bounty, all are pardoned, many preferred to places of Honor, Truſt and Reputation: And if you will but draw the Curtain, you ſhall ſee Sir <hi>Anthony</hi> ſitting as a Judge at the <hi>Old Bayley,</hi> helping to Hang Draw and Quarter his <hi>Quondam</hi> Maſters, whoſe treaſonous Commands he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly obeyed, but had the good luck to keep his hand from <hi>Bradſhaws Ink.</hi> So true it is, <hi>Ille Crucem ſceleris pretium tulit his Diadema;</hi> For not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe notorious Villains deſervedly got their Necks incircled with a Halter, Sir <hi>Anthony</hi> got his Temples impaled with a Coronet, being advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the honour of a Baron of <hi>England,</hi> and Chancellor of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer; and indeed running ſo very hard up the hill of his own Ambition, which was to be the <hi>Premiere</hi> Miniſter of State, very many who then obſerved it, made preſages of what hath ſince fallen out.</p>
            <p>Not long after, happened the difference between his Majeſty and the <hi>States</hi> of the United <hi>Netherlands;</hi> and as the Noble and never enough La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented Earl of <hi>Oſſory</hi> told him, (upon occaſion of his reflecting upon his Grace the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> in the Houſe of Lords, to which he was able to make no Reply) his little Lordſhip adviſed the <hi>ſhutting up of the Checquer,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93643:5"/>breaking the Triple League, ſeizing the Dutch Smyrna Fleet,</hi> and ſeveral other things, which ſince his Lordſhip and his Faction have ſo often charged as miſcarriages upon his Majeſties Government; and being now advanced to be Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> ſo ſollicitous was his Lordſhip for the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> that he made that famous Speech of <hi>Delenda eſt Carthago,</hi> animating the great Council of the Nation the Parliament, to proſecute the War againſt the <hi>Dutch,</hi> though Diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proteſtants, with the ſame animoſity, as <hi>Cato</hi> did the <hi>Romans,</hi> to the utter ſubverſion of the Pagan <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> to level the proud and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious City of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> after the example of that <hi>Affrican</hi> City, which conteſted with <hi>Rome</hi> for the Empire of the Univerſe.</p>
            <p>And here you ſee his Lordſhip upon the top of the Hill; but it was not long before he fell into the diſpleaſure of the Commons, who for ſome Councels of his, tending as they ſaid to the <hi>breach</hi> of their Priviledges, were framing Articles againſt him; of which by his Eſpials being adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, he immediately makes a ſhort turn, and ſtrikes in with thoſe of the Commons Houſe, who then called themſelves the <hi>Country Party,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Court Party,</hi> as they were invidiouſly diſtinguiſhed, and having the Purſe, Seal and Mace taken from him, which before hung in his eyes that he could ſee no ſuch matter, thoſe beams were no ſooner removed, but he pretended to ſee <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Government</hi> as plainly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in upon the Nation, as in a clear day a man may ſee <hi>Callis</hi> Sands from <hi>Dover</hi> Cliff.</p>
            <p>The whole Nation being in a violent agitation upon the <hi>Diſſolution</hi> of the Long Parliament and the <hi>breaking</hi> out of a Popiſh Plot, his Lordſhip who was admirable at the ſport of fiſhing in troubled Waters, was now got into his own Element, and reſolved at once to be revenged of all his Enemies, and who but he to be the head of the United Faction of Diſſenters throughout the Nation; by way of eminence, he had the Title of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Peer,</hi> as if all others who did not come under his protection had been <hi>Papiſts.</hi> All the Applications of the Party, all Informations, all Counſels and Cabals were at <hi>Thanet-Houſe;</hi> there the Proteſtant Joyner <hi>Colledg,</hi> and fourteen of the Jury who brought in the Bill againſt him <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus,</hi> who were of his Lordſhips Neighbourhood, the Anabaptiſt Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Harris, Jack Starkey,</hi> &amp;c. the Libellers of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Care, Ferguſon,</hi> &amp;c. found warm Entertainment; there was the conſtant Rendezvous of the Basket-hilted old <hi>Olivarian</hi> Officers, who had loſt their Crown and Church-Lands, there all thoſe miſchiefs were contrived which have given the Government and Nation ſo much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; thither the Green Ribbon Club and their Foreman Sir <hi>R. P.</hi> uſed to repair conſtantly to take their Meaſures for what was to be done in the Commons Houſe, there the famous <hi>Bill of Excluſion</hi> was hatched, which was to invade the Prerogative of God Almighty, as well as the Kings; from thence came the <hi>Seditious</hi> Addreſſes and Petitions of the <hi>Furious Diſſenters,</hi> inſolently to teach their Repreſentatives to demand the <hi>Militia</hi> of the King, to exhort him to part with his <hi>Evil</hi> Councellors; ſo they called, as they did his Fathers, the <hi>Loyal Nobility,</hi> Friends to the Crown and Church; promiſing to aſſiſt them in their demands with their <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes,</hi> and above all <hi>not to ſupply the King with a Penny of Money</hi> but upon <hi>thoſe</hi> Conditions, though at the ſame time, the Nation was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly alarm'd with the formidable power, and dangerous greatneſs and deſigns of the <hi>French</hi> King upon us. From thence came the Invention of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93643:5"/>ſtealing the Sword from the Kings Scabbard, by putting on ſuch Sheriffs as <hi>Bethel,</hi> who as it is averred under the Town Seal of <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> offered his ſervice to be the late Kings Executioner, and ſuch Sheriffs, returning ſuch <hi>true Proteſtant</hi> Juries, as would crack Oaths as faſt as a Squirril does Nuts, as <hi>Wilmores,</hi> &amp;c. who could return <hi>Ignoramus</hi> upon a Bill of Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>High Treaſon</hi> though ſworn by a thouſand legal Witneſſes: There was found the Traiterous <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> which was to overturn the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, and deſtroy not only Monarchy, but the very Eſſence and Conſtitution of Parliaments, veſting the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the hands of ſuch Perſons, as ſhould take that damnable Oath.</p>
            <p>It were endleſs to recount all the Speeches of this Noble Peer, made in the Houſe of Lords, not to <hi>truſt</hi> the King, or to <hi>give</hi> him Money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or the whole ſhoals of Lewd and Seditious Pamphlets, <hi>Letters to Friends, Appeals to the City, Dialogues between Tutors and Pupils,</hi> which were Written, Printed and Diſperſed by his Direction and Approbation; every Coffee houſe, every Town, City, and corner of the Land is full of theſe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous and diſloyal Papers; and the late abominable Pamphlet of the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part</hi> of the <hi>Growth of Popery,</hi> a Libel that has more Lies than Lines in it, as it is confidently reported came as a parting blow from his <hi>Amanu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis, <hi>Ferguſon.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>And they who ſaw his Lordſhip march with his <hi>Armed Guards</hi> to the Parliament at <hi>Oxon,</hi> will without difficulty believe, that the Deſign of <hi>ſeizing</hi> his Majeſties Perſon there was hatched in <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreet,</hi> and though, notwithſtanding the legal Trial of <hi>Colledg,</hi> and his Conviction for that Treaſon, 'tis endeavoured to ridicule that matter, yet I doubt not but a little time will make further clear diſcoveries of it to the world.</p>
            <p>But now we muſt think of bringing his Lordſhip to his Journeys end, for after all his endeavours, and thoſe of his Faction, to ſubvert the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, had proved inſucceſsful, and even his <hi>Iriſh</hi> Evidences, whom he drew over to accuſe his Grace the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> proving himſelf not only guilty of Subornation, but of Plotting againſt the Government, and the Tide of Loyalty turning very ſwift upon him, beyond his foreſight or expectation, his Lordſhip durſt not truſt to the innocence of his Actions, or abide the Legal Trial of his Peers; but thinking Heels the beſt ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for his Head, he reſolves to fly for the ſame, in hopes that the Treaſon which he had tap'd and left abroach at parting, might work ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as yet to give him the hopes of another ſqueek at leaſt for his Life; and whether ſhould his Lordſhip retreat but to that <hi>Carthago</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> which, had his advice been followed with ſucceſs, had not been capable of ſecuring his Lordſhip: But his Lordſhip found but very cold entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there, for the <hi>Delenda eſt Carthago,</hi> which was by publick Order of the <hi>States General</hi> entred upon their Books of Journals, came freſh into their Memories, ſo that he was neither Complemented upon his arrival, nor any notice taken of him by either the Magiſtrates or Miniſters of the <hi>Eſtabliſht</hi> Church there; nor indeed by any other ſort of People than a few pitiful <hi>Browniſts,</hi> the deſpiſed Diſſenters of <hi>Holland,</hi> ſuch perſons being his Companions, as had either fled from Juſtice like himſelf, or were the Sons of Traitors, and perſons diſaffected to the Perſon of his Majeſty and his Government, ſuch as Mr. <hi>Cromwel,</hi> Mr. <hi>Phelps,</hi> Mr. <hi>Venner,</hi> Mr. <hi>Medlay,</hi> Ald. <hi>Freeman Iſrael Hayes, Hayes</hi>'s Son, <hi>Thomas Garret;</hi> and <hi>John Starkey,</hi> who for printing divers ſeditious and treaſonable Pamphlets, was forced to leave the <hi>Mitre,</hi> and hang upon his Lordſhip for ſubſiſtance,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93643:6"/>but gave him little Reputation among the ſober and diſcerning <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of that Countrey, as will appear by a Letter from thence, to a worthy Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> and a Speech made to the Lords the <hi>Burge-Maſters</hi> by the late <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſul, which I ſhall here preſent the Reader with.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lords the Burge-Maſters,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Am come to take my leave of your Lordſhips, and to let you know, that the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> my Maſter hath thought fit to diſcharge me of any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther attendance in this City, in the quality of Conſul of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, his Majeſty being gratiouſly pleaſed to honour Mr. <hi>Henry Bull</hi> Merchant, with a Commiſſion to be Conſul in my place.</p>
                  <p>And now my Lords, I am come to give your Lordſhips thanks for the many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and civilites I have received during my reſidence in your City, as freeing me from paying thoſe Taxes and Duties your Burgers pay.</p>
                  <p>My Lords, give me leave to aſſure your Lordſhips, that during my living in your City, I have ſtudied all ways and means that might render me acceptable to the Magiſtrates and Government of our City, and ſo far as lay in my power have endeavoured to facilitate the preſerving a right and amicable underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſuch as deſerved the Character of <hi>Loyal Subjects</hi> to the King my Maſter, and the Burgers of this City; and my Lords, although I am called to other Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, yet wherever I am, or in what condition ſoever, I ſhall not ungratefully forget the Oblig ations I have received from your Lordſhips, but conſtantly wiſh and pray for the welfare and proſperity of your City, and do every thing in my power that may add to, or preſerve the now alliances between my Maſters Subjects and Yours.</p>
                  <p>My Lords, I have but one word more to ſay, and that is, that as I have now made my ſincere profeſſion of Friendſhip and Service to your Government and City, ſo I muſt beg leave to Caution your Lordſhips in one particular; I know your Lordſhips are wiſe in a high degree, and need no mans Advice or Caution, but as I look upon it as a Duty incumbent upon me to the King my Maſter, and the true reſpects I have for your Lordſhips, I cannot but take notice of ſome reports I meet with in your City, which are, that ſeveral bad men, obnoxious to the King my Maſter, and his Government; nay ſuch as have been ſo impudently bold as to Print and Publiſh Treaſonable and Seditious Libels againſt the Honour and Dignity of the King my Maſter and his Government, and againſt the Honour of his Loyal Miniſters of State, ſuch whoſe ſpirits are ſo turbulent, and Phanatically Seditious, that they are not contented to act miſchiefs againſt their own Prince and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment eſtabliſhed by Law, but have wiſhed the worſt of Evils to their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Neighbours and their Government, as may be ſeen by that uncharitable Speech <hi>Delenda Carthago:</hi> Now my Lords, I ſay if ſuch bad men as theſe ſhall fly hither, and be protected, and made Burgers of your City, it may as I humbly conceive, in time do prejudice to the fair underſtanding and friendly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liences now had between the King my Maſter and the <hi>States General,</hi> which may reach this City, the Conſequences of which, I leave to your Lordſhips wiſe and grave Conſiderations.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Letter I mentioned before was to this effect.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOur Letter of the <hi>15th</hi> of <hi>Jan.</hi> laſt, in which you ſent me a brief Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> Sir <hi>W. Waller,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ferguſon,</hi> came not to my hands until the very day that the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> died; yet I have made uſe of it, by giving Copies of it to ſome of our Magiſtrates, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93643:6"/>to ſome of the Preaching Miniſters of our Church, who believing his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to be ſuch a ſort of Chriſtian as you have repreſented him, are very glad that Providence hath eaſed them of ſo ill a Gueſt as he might have proved to be to their Government, fearing that his bad Principles might in time have poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned the giddy Mobile of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> as he had done in <hi>England; I</hi> hope his death will diſperſe the ſmall Inconſiderable Party he had with him in our City. When his Lordſhip firſt came to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> his Agents Mr. <hi>Ferguſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Iſrael Hayes</hi> and others, endeavoured to perſwade us, that there were ſeveral Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and above 200 Rich Merchants of <hi>London,</hi> that were all deſigned to guit <hi>England,</hi> and if poſſible get themſelves made Burgers of our City; all which proves very falſe, for I find that theſe great numbers of Rich Noblemen and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, are ſum'd up in a Bankrupt Knight, a ſcandalous <hi>Scotch</hi> Independent Parſon, formerly Teacher of the <hi>Browniſt</hi>-Church in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and about two or three miſerable poor Printers and Bookſellers, who now the Earl is dead, muſt either live upon the Poors Box of the <hi>Browniſts</hi>-Church, or elſe with Ropes about their Necks, beg their Pardons of the mercifulleſt of Princes: And here give me leave to remark ſomething you mention in yours to me, and that was where you ſay, <hi>that certainly the turbulent reſtleſs ſoul of the Lord</hi> Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, <hi>could not long ſubſiſt, and live amongſt ſuch a Raſcality of People as his Lordſhip had to converſe with,</hi> the which I underſtand was one great cauſe that haſtened his Death; for I am informed, that when he found that the Magiſtrates and Miniſters of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> did not viſit and court him, as was promiſed his Lordſhip by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Phanaticks at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing refuſed to be made an <hi>Upper Burger,</hi> as they term it here, and his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip receiving rather a diſcouragement from the Magiſtrates than otherwiſe, I ſay this was it which ſeemed to ſhorten his days, and ſo he died miſerably in a Broken Coffee-mans Houſe, one of the <hi>Elders</hi> of the <hi>Browniſt</hi>'s Church. I will ſay no more, but wiſh that all the Enemies of your King, this State, and the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> may make no honour abler an <hi>Exit</hi> than this once Great Peer of <hi>England</hi> hath done.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Yours to Command.</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>By this time you ſee in what Reputation our Noble Peer was like to have ſtood in <hi>Holland,</hi> as well as in <hi>England;</hi> and that we may commit him to his long repoſe, for his <hi>Religion,</hi> he was as good a Proteſtant, as any one can be ſupoſed to be, who could atheiſtically call the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> the <hi>New Cheat;</hi> his <hi>Fortitude</hi> was evident as well as his <hi>Loyalty,</hi> by the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage he had to oppoſe a moſt potent Monarch, and his Natural Liege Lord; Mother—to whom in his ſplendor, with the Purſe, Seal and Mace, he made a publick viſit, ſhall depoſe for the ſevere virtue of his <hi>chaſtity;</hi> and his timely flying from Juſtice, and opportunely dying, will demonſtrate his <hi>Conduct</hi> and <hi>Prudence;</hi> the Exiles who will want it, ſhall atteſt his <hi>Charity;</hi> the Diſſenters upon whom he hath, by animating them againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, intailed the ſeverity of the Laws, and left them fluttering in the Net which he had eſcaped, will ſtand obliged to him for their <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings;</hi> and I hope the King and the whole Nation whom he hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the Temper of men of his Principles, Deſigns and Faction, will have reaſon to thank him for their <hi>future</hi> Settlement and Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the <hi>Real</hi> Fears and Dangers of Phanaticiſm and Arbitrary Tyranny its inſeparable Companion.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:93643:7"/>
            <p>I have nothing more to add, but to wiſh the Diſſenters who have been fond of this Noble Peer even to Idolatry, to read in his, their own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny; there is a <hi>long Arrear</hi> due to them for the <hi>former Rebellion,</hi> the Blood and Rapine, the Sacriledge and Hypocriſy of them and their Fathers; and a <hi>new Reckoning</hi> too for their <hi>Inſolent Diſobedience</hi> to the beſt and moſt merciful of Princes, their <hi>ingratitude</hi> towards God and Men, their <hi>ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borneſs</hi> againſt the beſt Reformed Church in the World, and <hi>refractori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to the moſt Excellent Civil Government under the Sun, which they have as wickedly, as vainly attempted to ſubvert: They have had a long time given for Repentance, but they may ſee if they be not willfully blinded, that there is a time coming, if they withſtand Gods and the Kings Clemency and Mercy, when they ſhall be paid all this long Arrear; and in the opinion of many wiſe men, who have particularly remarked how Providence hath by their own folly baffled all their late Deſigns, blaſted their Hopes, and cut off the Engineers of the Faction, it looks as if they were even weary of that happineſs they might yet enjoy, and that with their own hands they would pull down thoſe puniſhments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own heads, which commiſerating Heaven and a Compaſſionate Prince have ſo long delayed to execute upon them; for certainly they muſt be weary of their Lives, and out of their Wits, who daſh out their own Brains againſt the Government in hopes to overturn its ſtrong Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. I wiſh they may recollect themſelves, and remember the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> who when he might have lived Glorious, Eaſy, and Happy by obeying his Prince, and Country Laws, died a miſerable, deſpiſed Fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, the <hi>Scorn</hi> of the <hi>preſent,</hi> and the <hi>Contempt</hi> of all <hi>future Ages.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
